Ricardo Rato

+351 964657580 • 7800-524 Beja, Portugal • ricardo.jorge.rato@gmail.com • https://www.linkedin.com/in/rjrato/

Software Engineer

Front End | Full Stack | Back End

Finishing CS50x from Harvard, a Bootcamp and enrolled in AWS Skill builder in order to start a bright career as Software Developer! Already Implemented some projects with C, Python, JS, HTML, CSS, SQL, Flask, Jinja. Always hunger for new knowledge and curious about new things, with a fantastic learning capacity. Great Systems Administrator background with over 9 years of experience and IT technician since 2007.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Portuguese Air Force - Beja

June 2007 to June 2013

Systems Administrator

- Successfully managed ServiceDesk support with over 500 network users
- Collaborated in hardware and software troubleshooting on a daily basis
- Proactively implemented network imaging service with Acronis service deployment, reducing each intervention time by 25%
- NATO and Portuguese Air Force secure network infrastructure maintenance
- Weekly Data Center backups and monthly server hubs maintenance
- Active collaboration on international missions with IT support
- Daily management of iPrint user permission groups and network access groups
- Intranet website administration
- Procedures documentation improving dramatically team response time
- Audiovisual support for each Air Base briefing

Freelancer IT technician - Beja

April 2007 to present

IT technician

- Hardware, software and networking domiciliary and remote support
- Printers installation and configuration
- Hardware fixing
- Workstations assembly

Municipally Council - Grândola

July 2014 to December 2014

Systems Administrator

- Restructured and optimized network infrastructure of the council, speeding it up by 50%
- Provided hardware and software troubleshooting on a daily basis
- Created Parish 3D interest points with AutoCAD and Google Sketch Up
- Cloud storage and respective security policies implementation, eliminating all redundancy

Decentralized Data Validator - Beja

- Fascinated about WEB3.0, embraced the possibility to contribute to the maintenance of the Ethereum protocol until the upgrade to *prove of stake* mechanism
- Custom servers assembly, cooling systems design and proper cable management reducing power consumption by 55% and temperature by 25 degrees Celsius
- ASIC installation and configuration
- Developing the first self-sustainable Web 3.0 Data Center in Portugal

GNR - Guarda Nacional Republicana - Beja

September 2015 to April 2018

Police Officer

- Report every known illegal activity to the court helping population to be safe and secured
- General population proximity patrol activities
- Traffic control and inspection
- Administrative duties
- Court diligences
- Public attendance in general

GNR - Guarda Nacional Republicana - Beja

June 2018 to Present

UEPS Agent

- Integrated Heli transported Teams, whose main mission is to be the first line support in rural fire fighting
- Executed numerous first intervention missions
- Integrated search and rescue missions
- Environmental and forest management control missions

Certifications and Courses

Harvard - online

CS50x – Introduction to computer science, finishing in January 2023

Udemy - online

The complete 2023 Web development Bootcamp, finishing in February 2023

AWS Skill Builder

Cloud Essentials Learning Plan, september 2022

AWS Cloud Practitioner quest, October 2022

Portuguese Air Force - Ota - Portugal

Military training and IT Operator Course – June 2007

FDTI – Évora - Portugal

IT support, May 2006

GNR - Figueira da Foz formation center - Portugal

UEPS Agent training, June 2018

GNR – Portalegre formation center - Portugal

Police Officer training, June 2018

EDUCATION

Antonio Inácio da Cruz High School – Grândola - Portugal

Physic, Mathematics and Computer Science, June 2004

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- C, Arrays, Algorithms, JavaScript, Python, Data Structures, HTML, CSS, Flask, jQuery, NodeJS, API, Git, EJS, SQL, Jinja, Visual Code, Github, Git
- VMWare, TeamViewer, Zenworks, Acronis, AutoCad, Sketch Up, Photoshop, Active Directory, MS Windows, MSOffice, OpenOffice
- AWS Cloud Essentials, AWS Cloud Practitioner, Docker, Kubernetes
- Team work environment and independently as well
- Organized and great problem solver capacity

AWARDS AND HONORS

Military Exemplary Behavior Copper Medal - Air Base N11, Beja

August 2013

 Award given for 6 years of exemplary military conduct, without any criminal nor disciplinary punishment.

Military Praise - Air Base N11, Beja

June 2010

 Recognized for outstanding dedication and excellent professionalism, contributing effectively for the promptitude and efficiency of the IT service in Air Base N11.

LANGUAGE COMPETENCIES

- Portuguese: native language
- English: fluent language